A Guide to the Montgomery County Bicentennial Commission Records 1972-1977
Digital Library and Archive, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Digital Library and Archives, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Montgomery County Bicentennial Commission Records 1972-1977
Digital Library and Archive, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Ms76-001
2 containers; 1.0 cu. ft.
Records of commission formed to organize events celebrating the 200th anniversary of the formation of the United States and Montgomery County, Virginia. Includes correspondence, minutes, working notes and papers, printed material, photos, memorabilia, and a scrapbook.
Donor
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Montgomery County Bicentennial Commission Records were donated to Newman Library in 1976 and 1977.
Biographical/Historical Information
The 200th anniversary of the establishment of the United States gave rise not only to national-scale celebrations but hundreds of smaller celebrations at the state and county level, as well. These commemorative events focused on communities' pioneer history and heritage and often coincided with the production of local histories and other commemorative materials. By coincidence, Montgomery County, Virginia also celebrated its 200th anniversary in 1976. In 1973, the Montgomery County Board of Supervisors created a commission to organize events which would not only commemorate the U.S. bicentennial but would also celebrate and preserve the history of Montgomery County, its communities and institutions. Chaired by Virginia Tech animal science professor George Litton, the commission also organized tours of local areas and designed commemorative items, including an emblem which is used today as the Montgomery County seal. The commission's activities culminated in the "Festival of Independence" celebrations in Blacksburg and Christiansburg, July 2-4, 1976.
Scope and Content Information
This collection contains the records of the Montgomery County Bicentennial Commission, which organized local events celebrating the 200th anniversary of the formation of the United States and Montgomery County, Virginia. The collection includes the correspondence of commission chair George W. Litton, and a set of the commission's minutes. Also included are records of the commission's committees, event planning notes and background materials, information on the design of the Montgomery County seal, programs and newsletters published by commission, and catalogs for bicentennial commemorative merchandise. Materials from other Virginia localities, statewide organizations, and national organizations are also included, as are a few photos and pieces of memorabilia. Completing the collection is a scrapbook-type compilation, assembled by the commission, providing an overview of its activities together with registration lists for the various events.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by document type.
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - 1973-1974 (Box-folder 1-1)
  - 1975 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - 1976 (Box-folder 1-3)
  - 1977, n.d. (Box-folder 1-4)
- Minutes 1974-1976 (Box-folder 1-5)
- Committees 1974-1975, n.d. (Box-folder 1-6)
- Event planning notes and preparatory materials 1975-1976, n.d. (Box-folder 1-7 (2 folders))
- Montgomery County seal n.d. (Box-folder 1-8)
- Newsletters and programs 1975-1976 (Box-folder 1-9)
- Bicentennial merchandise catalogs 1975, n.d. (Box-folder 1-10)
- Other local organizations and events 1972-1976 (Box-folder 2-1)
- Other Virginia localities 1973-1975, n.d. (Box-folder 2-2)
- Statewide organizations and events 1975-1976 (Box-folder 2-3)
- National organizations 1974-1976 (Box-folder 2-4 (4 folders))
- Photos and memorabilia 1976 (Box-folder 2-5)
- "Bicentennial Celebrations, 1976: Montgomery County, Virginia" [scrapbook] 1976 (Box-folder 2-6 (3 folders))